<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse wrytten by M. Theodore de Beza, conteyning in briefe the historie of the life and death of Maister Iohn Caluin with the testament and laste will of the saide Caluin, and the catalogue of his bookes that he hath made. Turned out of Frenche into Englishe, by I.S. In the yeare of our Lorde. M.D.LXIIII. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed in the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
            <title>Histoire de la vie et mort de Calvin. English</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1564</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837561</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837561</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1889</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1889)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 173:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse wrytten by M. Theodore de Beza, conteyning in briefe the historie of the life and death of Maister Iohn Caluin with the testament and laste will of the saide Caluin, and the catalogue of his bookes that he hath made. Turned out of Frenche into Englishe, by I.S. In the yeare of our Lorde. M.D.LXIIII. Seene and allowed according to the order appointed in the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
                  <title>Histoire de la vie et mort de Calvin. English</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
                  <author>Stubbes, John, 1543-1591.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Henry Denham, for Lucas Harrison, dvvelling in Paules Churchyarde at the signe of the Crane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[Anno Domini. 1564. Nouembris. 4.]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.S. = John Stubbs.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: Histoire de la vie et mort de Calvin.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliography.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:1"/>
            <p>A diſcourſe wrytten by M. Theodore de Beza, conteyning in briefe the Hiſtorie of the life and death of Maiſter Iohn Caluin, with the Teſtament and laſte will of the ſaide Caluin, and the Catalogue of his Bookes that he hath made. Turned out of Frenche into Engliſhe, by I. S.</p>
            <p>In the yeare of our Lorde. M.D.LXIIII.</p>
            <p>¶Seene and allowed according to the order appointed in the Queenes Maieſties Iniunctions.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Henry Denham, for Lucas Harriſon, dvvelling in Paules Churchyarde at the ſigne of the Crane.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>RIEND READER I offer vnto thee this preſent gathering or ſumme, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lyfe and Death of the Faithfull ſeruant of God, Maister Iohn Caluin: by the which thou ſhalt ſee maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous examples of the aſſaultes, that he hath endured for the Doctrine of the Sonne of God, and alſo what aſsistance God doth giue to his, when his honor and glorye commeth in question. In the meane time thinke it not ſtraunge that this diſcourſe doth not agree with the accustomed forme of Hystorians, for the purpoſe of the Auctor who is Master Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore de Beza, a good ſeruant of God alſo, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of Maister Iohn Caluin in the worke of the Lorde, was not to publiſhe it as an Hystorie, but onely for a Preface to the Commentaries of the ſaide Caluin vppon the Booke of Ioſue, come to light ſith his death. I haue thought good to aduertiſe thee hereof, to the ende that thou ſhouldeſt not thinke, that the memorie of ſo great and worthie a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage myght be ſatisfied with ſo ſmalle a diſcourſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:3"/> (albeit that it is diligently and truely ſet forth) the which ſhall ſerue thee onely to this purpoſe to make thee to hope and looke for an ample and goodly Hystorie of his actes and doings, which ſhall greatly profite to the aduancement of the Church of God: to whom be glory and honor for euer and euer. Sobeit.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Theodore de Beza,</hi> to the Chriſtian Reader, health and peace in our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it had pleaſed God to haue kept longer among vs hys Faithfull ſeruaunt Maiſter Iohn Caluin, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if the peruerſitie of the world had not cauſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord to take him ſo ſone to himſelfe: thys ſhould not haue bene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt of his labours, wherin he hath ſo faithfully &amp; ſo aptly emploied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the aduancement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of God, &amp; for the edification of his Church: And alſo now this Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarie ſhould not haue gone forth, without being as it were crowned w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Preface, as are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſt. But it fareth with it as it doth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poore Orphanes, which are not ſo well prouided for as their Brethren, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their father is to time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken from them. In this meane time I do ſee this Orphane to be of ſo good a houſe, thanks be to God, &amp; ſo well reſembling his father, that without any other Teſtimonie, he wil of himſelfe become not onely agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but alſo very honorable to all thoſe that ſhall ſee him. And therefore alſo mine intent
<pb facs="tcp:1889:4"/> hath not bene to recommende him by thys Teſtimonie, (for what needeth it?) but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lament more with him of the death of him, which hath bene as a father, both to him &amp; to mee: forſomuch as I neither may, nor ought to eſteeme him leſſe to be my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that which God hath taught mee by him, than this Booke, and ſo many others, which haue bene by him writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I will then bewayle mee, but it ſhal not be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: for hauing regarde to him of whom I ſpeake, I had rather haue had him lyuing here belowe, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felicitie wherin he is now placed, did not chaunge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorowfulneſſe of my loſſe into reioyſing of his gaine: and I ſhould ſmally haue profited by his ſo holye &amp; maruellous doctrine, &amp; by his lyfe that was ſo ſincere &amp; good, and by his death y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſo happy &amp; Chriſtian, if I had not learned by al theſe meanes to ſubmit my ſelfe to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of God, being fully contented and ſatiſfyed therwith. Now as concerning his doctrine, wherof I will firſt ſpeake, ſo farre vnable are the multitude which haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt him, to yelde it ſuſpected with all men of good iudgement, that on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the ſame might ſerue for an infallible ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to approue and confirme the ſame:
<pb facs="tcp:1889:4"/> for ſo much as none hath at any time ſtoode againſt it, but he hath well felt that he hath addreſſed himſelfe not againſt a man, but againſt a very true ſeruant of God. Alſo he maye lawfully affirme (and all thoſe who haue knowen him will be good and lawfull witneſſes) that he had neuer enimie, which in aſſayling of him made not warre againſt God. For after that God did cauſe his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion to enter within that lyſt or ſtecade, it may be well ſayde, that Satan hath picked him out euen as though he had forgotten al the reaſt, to aſſayle him, and to plucke hym thorowly downe, if he had bene able. But on the other ſyde God hath gyuen him that grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath adorned him with ſo many trophees or victorious tokens, as he hath ſet manifeſt enimies againſt him. If then wee ſhall ſpeake of the combats that hee hath inwardly indured for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine, there may nothing make them to ſeeme eaſy &amp; ſleight, but onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diligence which he did alwayes vſe, bicauſe he would not ſuffer his enimies to take breath, and the conſtancy which God gaue vnto him, neuer to yelde or bend how little ſo euer it were, in the quarell of the Lorde. The Anabaptiſtes can beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who ſhortlye after the beginning of
<pb facs="tcp:1889:5"/> his Miniſterie in thys Churche, to wit the yere <hi>.1536.</hi> that he could ſo wel and happily behaue himſelfe in open diſputation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe of the Magiſtrate, that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> race of them was vtterly deſtroyed in this Church: which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, bicauſe that the greateſt number of the Churches of Almaigne are yet at thys day greatly hindred by them: and if there be any that is free from them, it hath bene ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by rigour of Iuſtice than otherwyſe. He had an other combat to fight againſt an Apoſtate named Carol, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certain calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies &amp; falſe reportes: who beyng alſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen as well by writing as by worde, and caſt out of the Church of God, dyed mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerablye at Rome in an hoſpitall, as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to thoſe which do reuolte from Ieſus Chriſt, to folow a Maiſter which doth ſo wel recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his ſeruants, both in this world and in the other. And an other time, to wit the yeare of our Lord <hi>.1553.</hi> Michel Seruet a Spaniard of curſed memory, happened to come, who was not a man, but rather, an horrible Monſtre, compounded of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and new hereſies, and aboue all an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable blaſphemer againſt the Trinitie, and namely againſt the Eternitie of the Sonne
<pb facs="tcp:1889:5"/> of God: This ſame beyng come to thys towne, and apprehended by the Magiſtrate bicauſe of hys blaſphemies, hee was here ſo ſubſtancially encountred, that he had no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence but a certaine vntamed obſtinacie, by reaſon wherof by the iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God and man, hee ended by the punniſhment of fyre, his wicked life and blaſphemies which he had vomited, both by mouthe &amp; writing by the ſpace of thirty yeares &amp; more. About two yeares before there came a certaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitefull fryer a Carmelite, &amp; was ſodainly become of a deuine, a Phiſitian, named Hieroſme Bolſeck of Paris, who to get him eſtimation, thinking himſelfe to bee in Cloiſtre, and not in a Church of God, which he neuer did know but by heare ſay, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward being procured by certaine naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and euill diſpoſed perſons, of whom it ſhalbe hereafter ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, began in open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation to condempne the doctrine of the eternall prouidence &amp; predeſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though we made God the auctor of ſinne, &amp; culpable in the condemnation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked: Caluin in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> very place did ſtand againſt this diſguiſed Woolfe, &amp; did ſo anſwere him by word both ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly &amp; priuatly, &amp; afterward alſo by writing that the aduerſarie had no trouth of his ſyde
<pb facs="tcp:1889:6"/> remaining, but a certaine Monkiſh ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſenes, which made him &amp; doth make him at this day filthy &amp; ſtincking to euery man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath any good vnderſtanding: yea by his owne iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as ſhalbe declared by teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of hys owne hand whenſoeuer neede ſhal require. For this wicked man who had deſerued punniſhment for a ſeditious acte, beyng vſed by the Magiſtrate very gentlye, bicauſe that they thought that there might hereafter ſome remedie be founde for hys ſophiſticall ignoraunce, after that he had done ſo many offences and wickedneſſes as he was able in the Churches nere there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, ſeing himſelfe three times driuen out of the dominions of the Lordes of Berne, in the ende being intollerable to anye man, did giue glory to God, acknowledging hys errours: and eſpecially his euill conſcience, at Orleance in open general Synode of the Frenche Churches, the yeare <hi>.1562.</hi> in ſuch ſort that men had ſome hope in him. But after that being againe poſſeſſed by ſuche a lyke euill ſpirite, is retourned to his firſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and is driuen from all men, as hee is well worthy, and doth ſerue yet at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent daye in all places where he goeth, for a teſtimonie of the wrath of God againſt all
<pb facs="tcp:1889:6"/> ſuch as do reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. Shortly after there was a certaine remanaunt of Seruetiſtes, who declared themſelues, as one being a lawyer of thoſe quarters: who afterwarde for the lyke cauſe was driuen from the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of Tubing by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right noble Duke of Wirtemberg, and bicauſe he did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in his blaſphemies, for which hee had bene chaſtized by impriſonments and ſuffred to recant by the iudgement of the ſayd Lordes of Berne, with this man there was confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate a certaine man of <hi>Calabria</hi> named Valentine Gentill, an other of <hi>Sardegna,</hi> a <hi>Piedmontois</hi> named Iohn Paul Alciat, a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of <hi>Saluces</hi> named George Blandrata. Theſe men wrought vnder ground as well as they coulde, ſhewing their blaſphemies againſte the three perſons in one deuine Eſſence and beyng, vntill the time that this faithful ſeruant of God withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding them, ſome vaniſhed awaye, others of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging their blaſphemies, haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded mercy at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> handes of God &amp; of the Seignorie. But ſhortly after, thoſe wycked ones retourned (contrarie to theire othe) to theire blaſphemies, &amp; in the ende with their complices conueyed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into <hi>Polognia,</hi> where they haue ſtyrred vp and doe yet at
<pb facs="tcp:1889:7"/> this day, innumerable troubles, yet haue they notwithſtanding euen to &amp; in the very place where they are, felt &amp; perceyued what the force was of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull ſeruant of God, of whom we ſpeake: by whoſe writings the Churches of <hi>Polognia</hi> haue bene ſo fortified, that the Faithfull haue bene greatlye eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhed, &amp; the enimies of the truth ſo wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with the helpe of God, their ruine is at hande. Behold theſe are the principall combats that he hath fought within, for the doctrine, which is much more harde to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine than to reſite, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bookes ſhall teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to the poſteritie. As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other enimies, they haue alwayes aſſailed him from a farre of, but not ſo farre of, but that he hath tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched them more nigh than they would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly: his learned workes againſt the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes and Libertines can make ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t declaration. And as for the great Goliath Pighius, who was it that did beate downe and ouerthrow him and his Pelagianiſme, but only the power of the Lord in the hande of Caluin? who did ſhut vp the mouth of the glorious Cardinall Sadolet, but only hee? who hath more happily fought with &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hierde of Boares gathered togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deſtroy &amp; wroute vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Vineyard of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1889:7"/> Lord? who hath more greuouſly or more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilouſlye in deede wounded Antichriſt to the death? who hath more boldely &amp; more aptlye made anſwere to the wicked <hi>(interim)</hi> which hath ſo troubled Germanie? This is not all, for who hath bene of a more cleare ſight to knowe and to reproue the wickedneſſe of falſe Euangeliſts, who framed themſelues to all men meete? Who hath more conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puritie of the doctrine againſt the moſt daungerous kinde of enimies: to wit, thoſe which vnder the colour of peace and vnion doe endeuor the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to corrupt the puritie of the ſame? And as touching the miſerable contencion that was moued about the matter of the Supper, ſeyng the fire ſo greatly kindled, his whole deſire was to quenche it by a cleare expoſition of the matter; wythout naming of any man: the which he hath ſo wel and ſo aptly done, that he that ſhal wel conſider his writings, muſt confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next after God, it is to him, that the honor of the reſolution is due, which ſince hath bene folowed by all men of good iudgement. This notwithſtanding, Satan enforced himſelfe by all meanes poſſyble, to haue ſet deuiſion betweene hym and the Churche of <hi>Zuriche</hi> in thys diſcentyon:
<pb facs="tcp:1889:8"/> which among others hee hath alwaye eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and honored. But it was in vaine, for on the contrarie when they had in preſence conferred togither, they continued thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of one accord: and then was the conſent of all the Churches of Guiſe &amp; of the Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, framed &amp; imprinted in many tongues, to the great edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the people of God. That did much diſpleaſe certaine obſtinate men, among whom there was one named Ioachim Weſphale, an other Tilema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuſius, which were the moſte earneſt and feruent enimies of the truth and concorde. He was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enforced to entre into combat, whereby he dyd ſo maintaine the truth, and ouerthrowe and ſuppreſſe the ignoraunce and ſhameleſneſſe of ſuch perſonages, that he wonne great commendation, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue named great ſhame: yea euen among thoſe of their ſect &amp; nation, and the Church of God hath bene the more confirmed in the true and holeſome doctrine. In concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no hereſie auncient, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, nor newly forged in our time, which he hath not deſtroyed to the very foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For among al other his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Graces there were twoo that did ſhyne in hym: to wit, a ſingular ſharpneſſe of ſpirite to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:1889:8"/> where the difficultie of matters did lye, and then alſo a meruellous dexteritie and aptneſſe to make his aunſwers without the loſing of any one worde, as all they wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, yea the very enimies of the Goſpell, which would attentiuely reade his workes. I haue alſo omitted one Monſtre which hee lykewiſe did defeate, albeit that in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe I fought on hys ſide: it is one named Sebaſtian Caſtalion, who bicauſe hee had ſome knowledge in the tongues, and had alſo a certaine aptneſſe in the Latin tongue, he was here receiued to gouerne the ſchoole, But this ſpirite being ſo naturally enclined to pleaſe himſelfe, did ſo diue hym in his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, that in the ende he drowned himſelfe therein, bicauſe we coulde neuer winne ſo much of him, as to cauſe him to take the paines to reade the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries and other workes to reſolue him. That was the cauſe why he did openlye condemne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſong called <hi>Canticum Canticorum,</hi> in Latin, as a filthye and wanton Booke: which when it was layde to hys charge, he vomited out openly a thouſande iniuries againſt the Paſtors of this Church: Wherupon being commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrate to auouch his ſayings, and being conuinced of manifeſt malice and
<pb facs="tcp:1889:9"/> euill ſpeaking, by iuſtice he was appointed to depart the town after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged his fault: being then in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende retired to Baſil, hee continued there, vntill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the trouble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſtirred vp by Hieroſme Bolſec, vpon Predeſtination, the ſame man which helde alwayes of the perfection of the Anabaptiſtes, but it was ſecretelye and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his owne ſect, otherwyſe making no difficultie at all to ſhape hymſelf like to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and beyng alſo greatlye prouoked by the death of Seruet, he diſcouered hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf openly, firſt in a booke which he cauſed to be imprinted in Latin and in French vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a falſe and counterfeyt name of Martin Bellie, to whoſe errors and blaſphemies I haue aunſwered. Hee alſo made an other treatiſe which he calleth in Latin <hi>Theologia Germanica,</hi> vnder the name of Theophile, and in Frenche an other treatiſe of the olde and newe man. In the ende he did turne or rather ouerthrowe and confounde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Bible in Latin and Frenche with ſo vile a ſhameleſneſſe &amp; ignoraunce, that it is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that anye man coulde delight therein, were it not that newe things are alwayes agreable to Ambitious ſpirites, whereof there is at this daye as great plenty as euer
<pb facs="tcp:1889:9"/> there was. He did ſet before his tranſlation, an Epiſtle dedicated to the late good king Edwarde of Englande, whereby vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of preaching Charitie, he ouerthroweth the auctoritie of the Scriptures, as darke or vnperfect: to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende to ſende vs to perticuler reuelations, to wit, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreames of the firſt abuſer &amp; deceiuer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would declare and ſhew himſelfe. Hee did alſo make certaine notes vpon the ninth chapiter of the Epiſtle to the Romaines, wherby he doth ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly maintain Pelaglaniſme, &amp; doth not acknowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny decree and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, but only in thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are good of their own nature, forging in God a permiſſion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye to hys wyll, &amp; falſely laying to our charge, that we make God the Auctor of ſinne. All this did not any thing moue the faithfull ſeruant of God, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch calumnies &amp; errors had bene already aunſwered a thouſand times, vnto the time that hee himſelfe made a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine collection in Latin of certaine Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and arguments, which ſome men ſaide were taken oute of the Bookes of M. Iohn Caluin, adding thereunto certaine replica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: &amp; this booke was ſent cloſely to Paris there to bee imprinted, but God prouided for it and cauſed the firſte copye to come
<pb facs="tcp:1889:10"/> to my hands, in ſuch ſort that we our ſelues did cauſe them to be put in print here, wyth ſuch aunſweres as it did deſerue: hee after that he vnderſtoode the whole matter, knew not how to aunſwere the Paſtors and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Baſil, but ſayde that he was not Auctor of thoſe articles, being ſhortly after called to aunſwere vpon the doctrine of free wyll and of the prouidence of God, in open diſputacion at Baſil, hys doctrine was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. And bicauſe that certaine yeares before he had bene receiued to the profeſſion of the Greeke tongue, by thoſe that did not vnderſtande of hys errors, hee was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded not to deale neither by worde nor writing but with hys lecture, which thing he promiſed and did verye euill obſerue it, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing alwaies as he mought, in ſowing of hys errors and diſceiptes: and of a verye malice that he had againſt mee, who at that tyme was in Fraunce greatlye troubled, to my great griefe, in the ciuil warres: or at the leaſt beyng moued with ſome vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable ambition, hee wrote a little booke intituled, Counſell to deſolate Fraunce, without putting his name to it, or naming y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place wherin it was printed, albeit it was a free towne: in it doth he condemne all the
<pb facs="tcp:1889:10"/> French Churches of ſedition and rebellion, and giueth councell to euery one to beleue what he wyll, and by that very meane ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the gate to all Hereſies and falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines. I did not vouchſafe to make aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to that worthy counſell, which decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this man to be ouer beaſtly and ignorant in that whereof he did entreate, &amp; very euill exerciſed in ſuche affaires, but in the ſteade of it I did aunſwere to many pointes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee rebuketh mee, mingling with them moſt villaine and intollerable errors, vnder colour of defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that which I did miſlike in his Latin tranſlation. This myne aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere being dedicate to the paſtors of the Church of Baſil, was the cauſe that the ſame Caſtalion was called by the Churche and afterwarde by the Seignorie, and was commaunded to make aunſwere to that wherewith I charged him, and did offer my ſelfe to proue by hys owne writings: but within few dayes after death deliuered him from that trauaile. I knowe well that thys long diſcourſe ſhalbe miſliked of ſome men, as though I ſpake as a man loded with paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and coulde not be content to ſuffer the dead to be at reſt in their graue. But I may well proteſt before God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I did neuer hate
<pb facs="tcp:1889:11"/> the man in hys lyfe time, with whom alſo I neuer had to doe nether in good nor euill in perticuler, much leſſe that I woulde nowe hate and perſecute the deade which are put ouer to the iudgement of the Lorde. But it was needefull to make thys knowen, to the ende that euery man myght beware of hys Bookes and diſciples that hee hath left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him. Whileſt theſe things were doing, a certaine Diſciple aduaunced himſelfe, to wit, Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces Baldwin, who could no more continue in one Religion than in one place, but chaunged dwelling place &amp; condition in maner euery day, &amp; Religion at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt three times, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende hauing no more conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to looſe, he placed himſelf in a certain Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, like to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of Chanonnes Regulers, the which being ſuch in general as were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſt of al their troupe, yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is a queſtion of their perticuler, thei become Moncks in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that is profitable for the Monkes: and on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarie they be alwayes ſeculers, when Monkry pleaſeth them not: &amp; thys worthie perſonage did kiſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pantophle as the reaſt haue done, &amp; bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people ſhould be out of doubt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did it vnfainedly, he receiued a good and a worthy abſolucion of his king, to enter againe into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauour of his holineſſe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:1889:11"/> his Cardinals, vnto whom for recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all his euill hap he became ſlaue. If then it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in queſtion to haue one to write againſt vs, this is the beſt Catholique in the world: but on the other ſide if he muſt frame him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are as it were betweene twoo yrons, &amp; boaſt them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they holde the meane, then this good man ſpitteth out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſh Church, &amp; ſpeaketh ſtoutly of certaine abuſes, but it is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out touching the principal, &amp; in ſuch ſort notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which knoweth him not, would think he did meane good faith, &amp; not to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe him credite. This galaunt for his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, fayled not in the yeare .1561. to ſet forth a booke of ſuch ſtuffe, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any name, at the preſent time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men were at the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Poyſſy. Caluin vnderſtanding the meaning of this wicked one, made anſwere briefely according to his vſage: but verye paremptorilie and fully, giuing certaine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taints to him that was chiefely culpable of this euil. Baldwine vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to chafe, &amp; afterwarde left not to fome oute his rage againſt him whom he had ſo often called fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Maiſter, onely to make it knowen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was reuolted in deede, whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin did ouerthrow him, by one only ſilence.
<pb facs="tcp:1889:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> For as touching the iniuries and outrages againſt his perſon, he did alwayes eſteeme them honorable for the name of the Lorde whom he ſerued, forſomuch as to be blamed by a wicked man, is a token of vertue. And as for his reprehenſions concerning the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, the one ſort were ſo ſlender and ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper in his iudgement, that they deſerued no aunſwere, the others were but recitals borowed elſewhere, and refuted more than a thouſande times. And for ſo much as it is to me, that this Apoſtate hath alſo addreſſed him to gratifie his Maiſters, I haue taken vpon mee to aunſwere hym for the ſeconde tyme, which thing I hope alſo well to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, with the grace of our God. Theſe be the principall combats that this worthye perſonage hath happily endured for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of the Lorde. As touching the reaſt, in thys diſcourſe I thinke I haue entreated of the greateſt part of hys lyfe: for what was hys lyfe other than a continuall doctrine, as wel by worde as by writing, and by all his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and order of lyfe? the which alſo will doe very well to be declared perticularly, to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man may vnderſtande the maruels of God in the perſon of this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent man. Hee was borne in <hi>Noyon,</hi> an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb facs="tcp:1889:12"/> and famous towne of Picardie, the yeare .1509. the tenth of Iuly, of an honeſt houſe and of a reaſonable wealth, his father was named Gerard Caluin, a man of good vnderſtanding and counſell, and therefore greatly deſired in the houſes of noble men dwelling in thoſe partes: by reaſon wherof his ſaide Sonne was the better and more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berallye brought vp, at his fathers charges notwithſtanding, in company with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the houſe of Mommor, with whom alſo he was in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſchole at Paris. Hee was alway of a ſinguler good wit, and aboue all other things of a very good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, enimy to vices, and greatly giuen to the ſeruice of God as men did then call it: in ſuch ſort as his minde was wholy to deuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which was alſo an occaſion that he was prouided of a benefice in the Cathedrall Churche of <hi>Noyon.</hi> Yet was his father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes minded that hee ſhoulde ſtudie the Lawes, and he alſo on his part hauing alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane of a coſin and frinde of his, named Maiſter Peter Robert, otherwyſe <hi>Oliuentanus,</hi> who afterwarde tourned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble out of Hebrue into French and imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it at Neufchaſtle,) taſted ſome thing of the pure Religion, began to withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:1889:13"/> from Popiſhe ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: which was the cauſe that beſide the ſinguler reuerence that he had towarde his father, he did agree to go to Orleaunce to the ſame ende, where there did then reade an excellent ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named <hi>Peter de l' Eſtoille,</hi> who was afterwarde Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Court of Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Paris, vnder whom he did ſo profite in ſhort ſpace, that he was not accompted a ſcholer, but as an ordinarie Doctour, as oftentimes hee was rather in deede a teacher than a hearer, and he was offered to proceede Doctor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying anye thing, which thing alſo he did refuſe. And bicauſe that the vniuerſitie of Bourges was then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo famous by the meane of that excellent Lawyer Andre Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat which then did reade there, hee woulde him. In the meane time he exerciſed himſelf alſo ſee and heare in holye letters, with ſuch fruite and profite, that all thoſe whoſe heartes it had pleaſed GOD to touche, giuing them to vnderſtande what the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences were that were then moued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of Religion, did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye beare towarde hym ſinguler affection, but had him forthwith in great admiration for the learning and zeale that was in hym. Among other with whome he did frequent
<pb facs="tcp:1889:13"/> and companye, then at Bourges there was an Almaigne an excellent perſonage a Profeſſor of the Greeke tongue, named <hi>Melchior Volmar,</hi> whom I doe ſo much the more willingly remember, bicauſe it is very he that was my faithfull gouernor and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher all the time of my youth, for the which cauſe I will praiſe God all the dayes of my lyfe. Thys good man ſeyng Caluin not to be well inſtructed in the Greeke tongue, cauſed him to ſtudie the ſame, wherin he did greatly helpe him, as he himſelfe hath wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, dedicating to him hys Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries vpon the ſeconde Epiſtle of S. Paule to the Corinthians, and did him the honor to call him his Maiſter &amp; inſtructer. In this meane time his father died, which was the cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he left y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudie of the Lawes, and returned to <hi>Noyon,</hi> and then to Paris: where not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his youth, hee was not long vnknowen, nor without honor, by all ſuch as had anye feeling of the truthe: hee of hys parte dyd then reſolue to dedicate hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wholye to GOD, and did trauaile wyth great profyte in ſuche ſorte, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Paris in the tyme of the Rector na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Monſieur Copus,</hi> there happened a ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1889:14"/> whereupon hee was ſent to the Court to be preferred, where he was knowen and very well receiued of all thoſe that had any pure affection and ſounde iudgement in thoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres: In the ende ſeyng the miſerable eſtate of the Realme of Fraunce, hee deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to abſent himſelfe and to be where he might liue more quietly &amp; according to his conſcience. He then departed out of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the yeare <hi>.1534.</hi> and in the ſame yeare he cauſed to imprint at Baſil his firſt inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as an Apologie, dedicated to Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt Frenche King of that name, in the behalfe of the poore faithfull that were perſecuted, whom they did moſt falſely name Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes, to excuſe them towarde the Princes Proteſtantes, of the perſecutions that they then vſed againſt them. He paſſed alſo into Italie, where he ſaw my Lady y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ducheſſe of Ferrare, yet at this day liuing, thankes be to God, who when ſhee had ſeene &amp; heard him, forthwith iudged of him as hee was, and euer after vntyl his death, did loue and honor him as an excellent Organe of the Lorde. In hys returne from Italie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he had but ſeene, he paſſe (in a happie time) thorow this towne of Geneua, which not long before had receiued the Goſpell by the
<pb facs="tcp:1889:14"/> preaching of M. William Farell, and dyd meane nothing leſſe than to tarry there, but to paſſe thorow it and to go to Baſil, or elſe to Straſbourgh. But the Lord being euen then willing to prepare away to his ſo great goodneſſe as his pleaſure was to beſtowe vpon his Church by the meane of him, did put in the heart of the ſayde Farel to ſtaye him: which thing was very harde for him to doe, in ſuch ſort that after many requeſtes &amp; deſyres he was fayne to vſe adiurations. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to ſtay, not to preach, but to reade Diuinitie, and this came to paſſe in the yeare <hi>.1536.</hi> in the beginning of September. When hee was in this ſort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Doctor in thys Churche by lawfull election and auctoritie, hee then framed a briefe forme of Confeſſion and Diſcipline to giue ſome ſhape to thys new erected Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Hee made alſo a Cathechiſme which may be wel called one of his excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t works, and hath yelded maruellous fruite, beyng ſo well framed, that it was afterwarde tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of Frenche into Hebrue to winne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, into Greeke &amp; Latin for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcholes, alſo into Italian, Dutch, Engliſhe, Scotiſh and Fle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſhe, &amp; alſo Spaniſhe, for all theſe nations. Theſe proſperous beginnings dyd
<pb facs="tcp:1889:15"/> greatly miſlike Satan &amp; his, who failed not, (as it was an eaſy matter to doe in the firſt change of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſtate of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) to ſet himſelf againſt the proceding of the Goſpel. Albeit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was receiued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an oth by all thoſe of this town. Maiſter Caluin on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide as he was in deede of a noble minde, withſtoode firmely &amp; conſtantly with Maiſter Farel, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeditious perſons, hauing alſo on his ſide an other good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named <hi>Conrant,</hi> a Miniſter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of this Church, being blinde of his bodily eyes, but could wel ſee w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the eyes of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, whom alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Caluin had brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baſil, where he did remaine bicauſe of the great perſecutions, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were in Fraunce: The ende was ſuch, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord being min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded euen at once to take his ſeruant out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſſe, &amp; to purge this Towne of certain ſeditious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which did abuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel, to pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his name elſe where, &amp; laſt of al to frame his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by certain experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of things which did afterward ſtand him in great ſteade: it was ordeined (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel not being the beſt) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſhould depart y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> town w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in .24. houres, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wold not miniſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Supper of the Lord in a Citie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo troubled and ſtirred. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thys was declared to the
<pb facs="tcp:1889:15"/> ſaid Caluin, his aunſwere was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if hee had ſerued me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he ſhould haue bene ill reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, but he ſerued him, who in ſteade of euil recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, did alwayes giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more than they deſerued. And he might iuſtly ſo ſay: for he had folowed the example of S. Paule, in ſeruing of the Church vpon his own charges &amp; coſt. He then departed to the great griefe of all the good, firſt to Baſil, &amp; then to Straſbourgh, wher being receiued as a treaſure, by thoſe excellent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> M. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Bucer, Capito, Hedio,</hi> and others, who at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent did ſhyne as precious Pearles in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of God, hee there erected a French Church, &amp; therin did eſtabliſh Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline in ſuch ſort, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Almaignes could neuer yet attaine vnto, for their Churche, euen to this very daye: he did alſo reade Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great admiration of euery man, &amp; then he began to write vpon S. Paule, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarie vpon the Epiſtle to the Romaines to M. Simon Grinee, who was accompted to be the beſt learned of the Almaigne nation, &amp; was his great friende: he had alſo this grace among others, that hee brought to the faith a great number of Anabaptiſts which were ſent vnto hym out of all partes, and among others one named
<pb facs="tcp:1889:16"/> Iohn Stordeur of Liege, who within ſhort tyme after dying of the Plague at Straſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourgh, he tooke his widow to wyfe, whoſe name was <hi>Idelleto de Bure,</hi> a verye graue and honeſt woman, with whome hee liued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde verye quietly, vntyll our Lorde tooke hir away to himſelf, the yeare .1548. without hauing had any childe: at the ſame very time there were holden in Almaigne certaine imperiall aſſembles or diets for the matter of Religion, at Woormes and at Ratiſbone, in the which Caluin was choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for one of the chiefe by the aduiſe of all the Diuines of Almaigne, where he did ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his renoume became great euen among the very enimies, and Phillip Melancthon among others, did euen then receiue him into ſinguler friendſhip which did alwayes laſte afterwarde, and did then call him ordinarilye the Diuine, in token of ſinguler honor. In the meane time y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord did execute his iudgements at Geneua, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing certaine which beyng in the place of Syndique .1538. were the cauſe of the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhement of Caluin and Farel, in ſuch ſort as one of them beyng gyltie of a ſedition, &amp; thinking to ſaue himſelf thorow a window, did all burſt himſelfe, an other of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:1889:16"/> committed a murder, was by order of iuſtice beheaded, the other twaine being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced of certain vntrouth againſt the ſtate of the towne, fledde awaye and were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in their abſence. When the towne was purged of this froth, they began then to bewayle Caluin, &amp; he was deſyred thither againe by ſundry Ambaſſades fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Geneua, and by the interceſſion of the Lordes of Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riche, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords of Straſbourgh, who made great difficultie. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide Caluin ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how he profited in Straſbourgh, would in no wyſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent therunto, albeit to declare the good wyll that he bare to the towne, the yeare .1539. a whole yeare after hys baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hee maintained the cauſe therof or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the truth of God againſt the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sadolet, in a large and learned Epiſtle which is printed among the reaſt of hys workes. In thende he was threatened with the iudgements of God if he did not obey to that vocation, in ſuch ſorte that to the great ſorrowe of the Lordes of Straſbourgh, and eſpecially of Maiſter Bucer and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, he was licenced to be at Geneua for a certaine time. But when he came thither and was receiued of ſinguler affection by thoſe poore people which acknowleged their
<pb facs="tcp:1889:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> fault, &amp; hauing a great deſire to heare their faithful Paſtor, they helde him there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: wherunto in the ende the Lordes of Straſbourgh conſented, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> condition that he ſhould be alwayes a Bourgeois of their towne. They would alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould haue had alwayes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuenue of a Prebend which was appointed vnto him for hys ſcipende of his reading. But as he was a man clearely voide of all greedineſſe of the goodes of thys worlde, ſo coulde they neuer bring to paſſe that hee woulde receiue ſo much as the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of one Denier thereof. And in this ſorte he was againe eſtabliſhed at Geneua, the yeare <hi>.1541.</hi> the <hi>.13.</hi> of September, where forthwith hee framed an order of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Diſcipline, which hath alwayes ſince continued there firmely, albeit Satan and hys adherentes haue employed all theire forces to aboliſhe it. Now hee that woulde here declare particulerly all the trauayles &amp; paines that thys excellent perſonage hath endured ſince by the ſpace of <hi>.23.</hi> yeares as well within as without, hee ſhoulde haue matter ſufficient to fil a great volume. For if euer there were towne furiouſly aſſayled by Satan, and valiantly defended during y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme, it was Geneua, the honor belongeth onely
<pb facs="tcp:1889:17"/> to God, but it ought and may lawfullye be ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Caluin hath bene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of hys vertue &amp; power. If there be queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, Satan &amp; his could neuer take him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided, but either he hath warned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> flocke before hande, or elſe preſerued it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place. If wee ſhal ſpeake of integritie, he is yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſene him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any fault in his office, or to yelde, be it neuer ſo little, for any man liuing, or to haue varied in doctrine or life, nor neuer miſreported man. If we ſhall ſpeake of labour &amp; paine, I beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his like is not to be founde, beſide y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he preached co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually euery daye in the weeke, and moſt commonly, and as often as he was able, hee preached twice euery Sonday: hee did reade diuinitie three times in a weeke: hee made declaration in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Conſiſtorie or as it were a whole leſſon euery Friday, in conference of the Scripture which we call Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation, &amp; did continue this order thorowly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption vntill his death, &amp; in dede neuer did fayle ſo much as once, except it were by extreme ſickneſſe. Further, who is able to recite his trauailes ordinarie and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, I knowe not if any man of our tyme hath had more to heare, to aunſwere, and to write, nor matters of greater importaunce.
<pb facs="tcp:1889:18"/> The onely multitude and number of hys bookes and writings are ſufficient to aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe any man that ſhall ſe them: but much more thoſe that ſhall reade them. And that which maketh hys labours more wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, is that hee had a bodye ſo weake of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo lowe brought with watchings and ouermuch ſobrietie, yea and being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſo many diſeaſes, that all men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had ſene him, would haue thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he coulde not haue lyued at all. And notwithſtanding this, hee neuer left of day nor night his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in the workes of the Lorde: &amp; he coulde not endure to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> requeſtes and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of hys friendes which they daylye made vnto him, to the ende that he ſhoulde take ſome reſt. I wyll alledge onely two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. The yeare <hi>.1559.</hi> beyng aſſayled and maruellouſly greued with a feuer quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, he did notwithſtanding, in the chiefeſt of hys ſickneſſe, ſet forth the laſte edition of his Chriſtian Inſtitution, and did tranſlate it thorowe oute into Frenche. Likewiſe in his laſt ſickneſſes, which were the ſtone, the goute, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hemorrhodes, a Phthyſike feuer, ſhortneſſe of wynd, beſide his ordinarie diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the Miegrame, be did him ſelf tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late wholly that great volume of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries
<pb facs="tcp:1889:18"/> vpon the foure laſte Bookes of Moyſes: examined the tranſlation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt: made this booke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioſue, and did peruſe the greateſt part of the tranſlation and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations of the Newe Teſtament, in ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he neuer ceaſed from writing but only eyght dayes before his death, hys voice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to fayle him. Beſide hys innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable paines and his charges, in all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes and perilles, wherein this poore Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath bene, aſſayled within by many mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous and deſperate Citizens, tormented without a hundred thouſand wayes, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the greateſt Kings and Princes of Chriſtendome, bicauſe it was alwayes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and defence for all the poore children of God afflicted in Fraunce, Italie, Spayne, Englande, and elſe where, it was ſo that Caluin bare alwaye the greateſt burden: to be ſhort he myght well ſaye with S. Paule, who is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is troubled &amp; I do not ſorrowe? And it was not without cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had his refuge to him: for God had adorned him with ſo wyſe and good councell, that neuer man repented him of the following of it, but I haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many fal into great and extreme inconueniences which would not beleue him. Thys hath bene founde ſo
<pb facs="tcp:1889:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> by many experiences and proofes, namely in the ſeditions that happened the yeare .48. 54. and .55. to breake and diſorder the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church, where he thruſt himſelf naked in among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwordes drawne, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys preſence &amp; wordes he ſo frayed the moſt deſperate mutines of them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to prayſe God. The lyke was in the conſpiracie <hi>Catilinarie,</hi> which was the verye yere .55. to haue murdred all the French, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Captaine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne named <hi>Amied Perrin</hi> and his conſpirators, which coniuration ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with it a maruellous number of dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and trauayles, in the ende, the Lords of hys great grace, by the wyſedome of hys ſeruaunt brought it to that paſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is now at: to wyt, to the greateſt quietneſſe and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer this Citie did knowe. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his ordinary life &amp; dyet, euery man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> witneſſe that it was ſo temperate, that ther was neuer exceſſe in it, no more was there of nigardiſe, but a commendable meane, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that he had alwayes to ſmall regarde to his health, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented for the ſpace of many yeares w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one repaſt in .xxiiij. houres, and neuer receiuing any thing betwene his meales in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all that euer the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians could perſuade him vnto in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> point,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:19"/> was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> about half a yere before his laſt ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he did take at times about noone a litle wine and would ſoupe of an egge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes were the weakeneſſe of his ſtomack, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miegrame, for the which he ſaide hee coulde neuer find any remedy but a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual dyet, in ſuche ſort as I haue knowen him often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to eate no meate in two dayes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſo ſmal a dyet, he ſlept very little: &amp; for the more parte he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to warme him vpon his bedde, whereon alſo hee hath made the greateſt number of his bookes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continually happily occupyed in ſpirite. This is the order y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this excellent ſeruant of God did continuallye obſerue, forgetting himſelf to ſerue God &amp; his neighbour in his vocation &amp; charge: yet coulde hee not ſo doe but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Satan did rayſe vp againſt him al the ſhamefulleſt ſlaunders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is no newes, for it is the rewarde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the world in all ages hath giuen to thoſe that woulde drawe them from perdition. I wyll not aunſwere thoſe that doe call him Heretique and woorſe than Heretique, (whereupon they haue forged a name of Caluiniſtes) for hys Doctrine maketh aunſwere on the contrarye more than ſufficientlye. Some haue charged hym wyth ambition,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:20"/> but if they be able in anye point to proue it, I am content to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned. Is there any man that hath folowed greater ſimplicitie in the expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Scriptures, and hath more wherewith to ſet hymſelfe forthe if hee woulde haue profaned the Scriptures with ſubtile and vaine oſtentations? Hee would rule all, ſaye they. O villaine &amp; falſe ſhameleſneſſe: what preheminence did hee euer ſeeke? &amp; if he had ſought it, who coulde haue kept him from it? with whom did hee euer ſtriue for the firſt or the ſeconde place, when men haue not giuen vnto him that which the giftes and graces that God had giuen him did require? when hath hee bene ſeene alter, be it neuer ſo little? when hath it bene ſene that euer hee did abuſe his charge and his auctoritie towarde the ſimpleſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world? when did he take in hande any thing without the aduiſe or againſt the opinion of hys companions? To be ſhort, what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence was there euer betweene him and vs, but that he did excell vs all in all humilitie among other vertues, and alſo in that hee tooke more paine than all we did? was there any man more ſimplye apparelled or more modeſt in al reſpectes? was there any houſe conſidering the eſtate of the man, I doe not
<pb facs="tcp:1889:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaye leſſe ſumpteous, but more ſlenderlye furniſhed with moueables? And if men wil not beleue mee and ten thouſand witneſſes with mee, at the leaſt let them beleue the ſlender wealth of hys brother &amp; onely heire, and alſo the inuentorie of all his goods, and it ſhall be founde that all that euer hee lefte behinde him (accompting alſo hys bookes which were dearely ſolde bicauſe of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious memorie, to all men that were lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) doth not exceede the value of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred crownes. Theſe maye alſo aunſwere theſe ſhameleſſe euill reporters who haue talked ſo largely, that the one ſorte ſayd hee was a Vſurer, the other that he was a very bancker: a matter ſo worthie of ſcorne and ſo falſely rayſed, that anye man that euer did knowe him, wyll neuer require aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to ſuch an vntrouth. He was ſo coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous that hauing in the whole ſixe hundred Florines for his ſtipende, which doth not al amount to three hundred liures tournois, yea he ſought to haue leſſe, &amp; the accomptes of this Seigniorie can witneſſe it. Hee hath bene ſo couetous of thys worldely goodes, that being in fauour, yea &amp; honored both of Kings, Princes &amp; Lordes of many nations, and hauing dedicated his workes to them,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:21"/> I know not (and I think I ſhould haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen it if it had bene otherwiſe) that euer he receiued of them to hys vſe the value of .xx. Crownes. Alſo he had the ſacred woorde of God in ſuch reuerence, that he had rather to dye than to vſe it as a bayte to Ambition or auarice. Hee did dedicate hys bookes to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſons, acknowledging ſome benefite or friendſhip, as he did a very learned &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the booke of Seneca concerning the vertue of Clemencie &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, which he wrote in Parris, being of the age of .24. yeares, &amp; did dedicate it to one of the Lordes of Monmor, wyth whom hee had bene brought vp, not at theire charges notwithſtanding. The like hee did with his Commentaries vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Epiſtle of S. Paule to the Romanes, being dedicated to Simon Grinee: vpon the firſt to the Corinthians, to the Lord Marques Caraciol: vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſecond to the Corinthians, to Melchior Volmar his Maiſter that taught him the Greeke: vppon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to <hi>Mathurin Cordier</hi> his gouerner in the colledge of S. Barbara at Parris in his firſt youth: vpon the ſecond, to Benet Textor his Phiſitian: vppon the Epiſtle to Tite, to his two ſinguler friends &amp; companions in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, Maiſter
<pb facs="tcp:1889:21"/> William Farel &amp; M. Peter Viret: and the booke of offences to Lawrent of Norma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>die his auncient &amp; continuall friend. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> others which hee did dedicate to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Kings, Princes, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthes, his meaning was to encorage the one ſorte to perſeuer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, &amp; to ſtirre vp the others to the lyke. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo when he ſaw y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch men did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he made not ſtraunge to put out their names &amp; to put in others, which onely came to paſſe in two of his Prefaces. This be ſaid as touching this crime of auarice. Others on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide haue reported him to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall &amp; a player, but it was as true as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charged him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As concerning prodigality &amp; the fruites therof, hys bookes wyll well declare euen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of the world, of his paſtimes, &amp; of the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of ſuch lyers. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it is maruell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> durſt ſo farre to ſtray, as to forge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil report, were it not that it is a thing accuſtomed againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt excellent ſeruants of God. But he is yet vnborne that euer did ſuſpect him of whom we ſpeake in any place wherſoeuer he vſed: hee liued about nine yeares in Mariage ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye chaſtely, when hys wyfe was deade,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:22"/> hee continued in wydowerhead aboute the ſpace of .xvj. yeares, euen to hys death. In all that time who is he that euer percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the leaſt token that might be of ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie an acte in him? And what woman was there ſo villaine and ſhameleſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> durſt to beholde without ſhame a forehead ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende and ſhewing to all men that did beholde it, all puretie and fredome? Who hath bene a more rigorous enimy to whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome than he? It is true that the Lord hath exerciſed him touching this matter toward ſuch as touched him neare. There hath yet worſe happened in the houſe of Iacob and Dauid, than to him of whom wee ſpeake, and in a more ſtraunge ſorte. But what did Satan in this behalfe gaine of the faithfull ſeruaunt of God, but only ſhame &amp; rebuke to himſelfe in the later daye before the ſeate of the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God? And now to them that hee had ſtirred vp, to rayſe ſuch ſclaunder, Whoredomes, Adulteries, and inceſtes, are accompted for paſtimes and exerciſes of the wicked ones, in ſort, that one of the greateſt faultes that they finde with the reformed Churches, is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there whoredome and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie is puniſhed: In the meane while if there be any ſuch fault or offence founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:1889:22"/> vs, albeit that it be extremely pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, they accuſe vs with open mouth. In ſo doing, (if they ſayde truth,) what other thing doe they than blame vs in that that we reſemble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? But without entring any further into this diſcourſe, it muſte needes bee, (will they or no) confeſſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the theeues do not haunt where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrates &amp; Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates are: but to exerciſe ſuch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs it were more meete to dwell among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where ſuch offence is a vertue. But to returne to my purpoſe, it ſhalbe well founde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruant of God hath ſhewed to all the worlde a ſinguler example, in condemning this villaine and ſtincking vice, as well in them as in others: for when there were any found faultie, he had no regarde at al w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out accepting of perſons, but to GOD and hys Church: and I ſay nothing in thys, but that which all ſuch as did knowe hym well, wyll teſtifie before God. Ther haue bene others which haue named him to be irreconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, cruell, and alſo bloudye, which ſome of them woulde moderate, naming him only, to ſeuere. The defence is ſone made, God be praiſed, and it ſhoulde not be neceſſarie, were it not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhal do well to rebuke ſome of them for their peruerſitie, and to aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb facs="tcp:1889:23"/> the others of their ingratitude towards God. I ſayde in the beginning that which I doe now ſaye, which is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he neuer had eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies but ſuch as did not knowe him, or elſe ſuch as made open warre againſt GOD. I wil bring forth to witneſſe the ſame, a proofe more than ſufficient, it is, that hardely may there be any man founde in our time of hys calling, againſte whom Satan hath made more cruel warre by al kindes of outrages, but he neuer purſued any man in any court nor attempted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law againſt any, no, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſought any reuenge: alſo hee neuer had houſe nor enheritaunce, nor neuer did deale w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any traffique or occupying whatſoeuer it bee, but it is very true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when they banded againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of God which he taught, hee woulde neuer yelde in any thing, but would according to the holy lawes that bee here eſtabliſhed, proſecute, that the mockers of God might be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled according to theire deſert. But which are they that will blame that, but onely thoſe that doe tranſforme a vertue moſte rare and ſinguler, into a vice ouermuch common and hurtfull. By the waye, what if I ſay, and may lawfully ſay it in deede, that a number eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe againſt whom hee hath bene enforced to ſtande for
<pb facs="tcp:1889:23"/> matters before recited, haue honored his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie by their own teſtimonies? I coulde name at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt thre, which I wil not name, notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding twoo of them being brought to puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for their faults &amp; offences, did in the ſight of all the people, thinke all the honor &amp; thanks y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might yeld vnto him during the ſame, not to be ſufficient, calling him their Father, crying out, ſaying, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were vnworthie of hys preſence, aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; prayers, conſidering they had not harkened to his fatherly admonitions. The third being in his bed ſick eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death, who had bene during his lyfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſeller of all theſe ſtrayed ones, coulde neuer be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God would forgiue him, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whom he had ſo much offended, did not alſo forgiue him. So far were theſe men of from charging him either w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cruelty or ouermuch ſeueritie. I confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee hath alwayes ſhewed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrates, how dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> accepting of perſons is in the ſight of God, that they muſt holde the Balaunce aright: &amp; that God abhorreth not only thoſe which doe condemne the innocent, but alſo thoſe which pardon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offender. Now if it be vice to ſay ſo, &amp; to put it in vſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt muſt then be condemned who hath ſo ſaide:
<pb facs="tcp:1889:24"/> or if it be otherwiſe, ſuch blaſphemers that doe call the ordinance of God, crueltie, muſt haue their mouthes ſtopped. But, ſay they, he was ouer rigorous againſte adulterers and heretiques. I may well aunſwere that which is true, as all the towne doth know, that hee neuer iudged anye man, for it was not his office, and he neuer thought to do it: &amp; if they haue demaunded his aduiſe, not to confounde the eſtates which God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, but to be gouerned according to the worde of the Lorde. I knowe well that I myght auouth it, if I ſayde that they haue not alwayes folowed his counſell. But lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that, what are theſe mercifull cenſors able to alledge, when I ſhall ſay vnto them that which is true, which is, that there was neuer yet good gouernement in anye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth wherein adulterye hath not bene iudged worthy of death: and yet it can not be proued that any one ſimple adulterer hath bene punniſhed in this Citie by death. As concerning Heretiques, where is, I pray you, that great rigour? where is it that this bloudy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ſhewed one iote of a bloudy nature? There are fewe townes of Guiſſe and of Almaigne where they haue not put Anabaptiſtes to death, and lawfully: they
<pb facs="tcp:1889:24"/> haue bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented here with baniſhment. Bolſec hath here blaſphemed againſte the prouidence of God. <hi>Sebaſtian Caſtalion</hi> hath here ſpoken euill of the very bookes of the holy Scriptures. Valentine hath here blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſſence of God: None of them haue here bene put to death, twoo of them were onely baniſhed, the other was ſet free by an honorable amendes towarde God and the Seignorie. Where is this cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie? Only one Seruet was put to the fire. And who was euer more worthy than that wicked one, hauing for the ſpace of thirtie yeares in ſo many ſundrie ſorts blaſphemed againſt the Eternitie of the Sonne of God, giuing the name of <hi>Cerberus,</hi> to the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the three perſons in one onely Diuine eſſence, making the baptiſme of yong chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of no value, hauing gathered and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped togither all the filthy ſtinckes that euer Sathan did vomite out againſt the truth of God, hauing ſeduced an infinite number of perſons, and for the chiefe and principall of all his wickedneſſes, would neuer neyther repent in giuing place to the truth, wherby hee had bene ſo often times conuinced, nor ſhewe any token of conuerſion. And if wee ſhould come to the iudgement of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:25"/> who would not rather alowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which al the Churches of Almaigne, and namely Philip Melancthon a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greatly renoumed for hys meekeneſſe, hath not only ſpoken, but alſo publiſhed by writing, the prayſe of ſo iuſte an execution? To ende this matter, they which diſcommende ſuch an act, coulde neither better ſet forth their ignoraunce in blaming y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which deſerueth ſinguler com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, nor yet their raſheneſſe, when they deale wyth him who did but the office of a faithfull Paſtour, putting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrate in minde of hys dutie, endeuoring him by all meanes to bring ſuche a wicked man to ſome amendement, and in the ende, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting anye thing that might let that ſuch a peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhould not infect his flock. There are others which haue reported hym to bee very cholericke, I wyll not make of a man an Angell, yet notwithſtanding, bicauſe I do know how maruellouſly God hath bene ſerued by that ſame very vehemencie, I ought not to keepe ſilent that which is true, and that I doe know. Beſyde his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination to choller, hys witte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maruellous prompt, the folly of many, the multitude and infinite varietie of the
<pb facs="tcp:1889:25"/> affaires for the Church of GOD: and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the later ende of hys lyfe, hys great and continuall diſeaſes, had made him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and frowarde: but ſure hee was farre of from any delight therein, for on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, no man did better perceaue nor ſo much finde it as did hee. Thys be ſayde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning hys lyfe and conuerſation in hys houſe, in whome this onely default (that euer I knewe) was tempered wyth ſo great and amiable vertues, and ſo ſeldome or neuer at all acompanied with other vices which are alwayes wont to folowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, that he neuer offended any of hys friendes neither in woorde nor deede. But as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in publique concerning the charge that GOD had committed vnto him, it is there that I muſte needes maruell at the great wyſedome of God, turning all things to hys glorye, and chiefely in hys moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler inſtrumentes and Organes. Such as haue ſeene and knowen wyth what kinde of men he hath moſte commonly had to doe, the thinges that God hath declared and done by him, the circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of times and places, they in deede may iudge wherto ſuche a vehemencie, I ſay, a vehemencie in
<pb facs="tcp:1889:26"/> déede Propheticall, did ſerue and ſhall ſerue to all poſteritie. And that which made him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore maruellous, was, that nether hauing nor ſeeking any thing leſſe than that which is ſo muche required by thoſe that would be feared by meane of an outward apparance, the moſte obſtinate and peruers were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to bende vnder the great power of God, which did compaſſe about his faithful ſeruaunt. They which ſhall reade his wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, and ſhall rightly ſeeke the glory of God, ſhall there ſee this maieſty (whereof I ſpeake) to ſhine. As concerning ſuch as doe at this day handle religion, as they doe poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique affaires, which are more cold than yſe in Gods cauſe, and more enflamed than the fire, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which concerneth their particuler cauſes, and which doe cal al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> choller, which is more frankly ſpoken than they woulde, euen as he neuer ſought to pleaſe ſuch men, euen ſo doe I thinke it not meete to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the anſwering of them. What would theſe wiſe &amp; temperate men ſay then, (ſeing there is no queſtion but of God,) if they had more earneſtly felt ſuch a choller? I am ſure they would haue bene alſo on their part as euill contented, as I doe thincke, and ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:1889:26"/> thinke my ſelf happy during my life, to haue enioyed ſo great and ſo rare a vertue, bothe openly &amp; priuately. Euen as I coulde neuer be weary of ſolacing my ſelf in the abſence of ſo worthy and excellent a perſonage, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting him vnto me by the diſcourſe of his rare and exquiſite vertues: no more can I without very great ſorowe, make an end of that which reſteth, and may notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in no wiſe bee lefte vntouched, for ſo muche as it is, as it were, the crowne and beautye of all his life. Beſide that God did place this great wiſdom and vnderſtanding in a weake bodye, and diſpoſed of it ſelfe to the diſeaſe of the Pthyſike, whereof he alſo died: the ſtudies of his youth had made him verye leane and weake, and when he came once to the affaires, he had alwaies ſo ſmall reſpect concerning the trauaile of his mind, that withoute the ſpeciall grace of GOD, (whom it pleaſed to builde his Churche by the meanes of that inſtrumente) it had not ben poſſible for him to haue come to the age which the Phiſitians doe call the declining. The yeare <hi>.1558.</hi> being required by the Lordes of Franckfort to make a voyage thyther, to appeaſe and prouide remedie for
<pb facs="tcp:1889:27"/> certaine troubles that were in the Frenche Church, which was newlye receiued in to that towne: at the retourne of thys long &amp; trauaylſome voyage, he had a tercia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feuer, very ſharpe, which was as it were the firſt puſhe at hys health: in ſuch ſorte that in the yeare of our health <hi>.1559.</hi> hee was aſſayled with a long and perillous feuer quartane, during the which, to his great grief, he was enforced to abſtaine from both preaching and reading: but hee was neuer vnoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyed in his houſe, what counſell ſo euer me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaue him, in ſort that during that time, hee began and ended his laſt Chriſtian inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution both in Latin and in French, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee will ſpeake in the concluſion. Thys ſickneſſe brought him ſo lowe, that neuer afterward he coulde recouer his full health, he drewe euer afterwarde hys right legge after him, which oftentimes did greatly greeue him: his auncient diſeaſes put them in order alſo: to wit, the head ache, and great rawneſſes which cauſed a continuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxion: hee was alſo greued with the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhoides, ſo much the more in that that at ſome other time by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that part was made verye weake: the cauſe was for that he neuer ſuffered his minde to reſt. He had
<pb facs="tcp:1889:27"/> a continuall vnperfect digeſtion, wherunto he neuer gaue any heede, but when the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe compelled him. The colliques alſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and then in the ende the goute and the reaſt. Beſide this, by ſtrayning himſelfe, and by a gnawing defluxion, hee fell into a ſpitting of bloud, which did weaken him to the vttermoſt. In the middeſt of ſo many diſeaſes, it is a thing very ſtraunge that this ſharpneſſe of Spirit was rather letted than diminiſhed, and this dexteritie of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nothing altered. There was only this euil, that the body coulde not followe the ſpirite, albeit that he did ſometime enforce himſelf, vntil the time that he was ſo grieued wyth the ſhortneſſe of his wynde, that with great paine hee was ſcarcely able to remoue hym twoo or thre paces. The Phiſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s employed all their induſtrie, and he on his ſide did fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their counſel to the vttermoſt, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his griefes &amp; ſo many diſeaſes togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mingled. But it was all in vaine, as he did alwaies ſay, looking vp to Heauen, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king often theſe wordes, Lorde how long? And then in the ende he remained without ſtirring, hauing yet the vſe of hys ſpeache, but could not long ſpeake or continue any purpoſe by meane of the ſhortneſſe of his
<pb facs="tcp:1889:28"/> breath, yet notwithſtanding this, he ceaſſed not to laboure. For in this laſte ſickneſſe, as hath ben aboue ſaid, he did wholly tranſlate out of Latin into frenche, his Harmony vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Moyſes, did peruſe the Tranſlation of Geneſis, wrote vppon this booke of Ioſue: and in the ende did peruſe and correcte the greateſt part of the Frenche notes vpon the Newe Teſtament, whiche other men had before hande gathered. Beſide this he was alwaies occupied in the affaires of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, anſwering by worde and by wryting, when occaſion required: all be it that on our parte wee made requeſt vnto him, praying him to haue greater regard to himſelf: but his anſwer was alway to vs, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he did was nothing, requiring vs to ſuffer, that God mought finde him alwaies wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and labouring according to his abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his worke, euen to his laſt breath. The xxv. of April, he made his Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in brief ſort, as he did alwaies auoid the vſe of moe words than neded, as much as in him was. which doeth containe an excellent and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler teſtimony for euer, that he ſpake as he beleued, which was the cauſe that I did willingly inferre this ſame, word by word,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:28"/> by the conſent of his brother and only heire <hi>Antonie Caluin,</hi> to the end that this acte may remain for euer, as it hath pleaſed God that the Teſtaments of ſome of his moſte excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſeruauntes haue bene enregiſtred, to be perpetuall witneſſes, that one very ſpirit of God did gouerne them, both in their life, and in their death: and alſo to make the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowen the extreme ſhameleſſeneſſe of ſuche as would beare men in hand that hys death was not according to his life. And if any man doe thincke any thing to be herein other than trouth, I will not ſtand much in ſaying againſte him: onely I doe gyue him warning whatſoeuer he be, to thinke what thing it is, that maye be true and firme among liuing men, if it be lawfull for a man to dout that which hath bene done in a Towne, in the ſighte and knowledge of ſuch as wold heare or vnderſtand it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Calvins_will">
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:29"/>
            <head>The Teſtament and laſt VVill <hi>of Maſter Iohn Caluin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the name of God. Be it known and apparant to all men, that in the yeare 1564. and the .25. day of Aprill, I Peter Cheuelat, Citezen and Notary ſworne of Geneua, was called by the famous Iohn Caluin, miniſter of the worde of God in the church of Geneua, and Burgeſſe of the ſaid Geneua, being ſicke and weake of his body only: the ſame man declared to me that he would make his Teſtament and declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his laſt will, deſiring mee to wryte it accordinglye, as he ſhoulde ſpeake and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it: which according to his requeſt, I made, and wrote it by him, and accordingly as he ſpake and pronounced it to me, worde by worde, without leauing any thing oute, or adding any thing there vnto, in forme as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN the name of God, I Iohn Caluin Miniſter of the word of God, in the Church of God of Geneua, (feeling my ſelf greatly oppreſſed with ſundry diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, that I can not otherwiſe thinke, but that God wil ſhortly take me out of this world) haue determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to make and put in wryting my Teſtament and declaration of my laſte will, in forme folowing: which is, firſt of all, that I giue thankes to God, for
<pb facs="tcp:1889:29"/> that he hath not only had pitie on me his pore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to take me from out of the bottomleſſe pitte of Idolatry, (wherin I was plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged,) to draw me to the light of his Goſpell, and to make me partaker of the doctrine of ſaluation, wherof I was to much vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: and that continuing his mercy, he hath ſpared me in ſo many vices and wickedneſſe, whiche dyd well deſerue that I ſhoulde be caſte of from him, an hundred thouſand times: yea and that whiche more is, he hath ſtretched his mercy towardes me ſo farre, as to be ſerued by me and my labour, to beare and to ſhew forth the truth of his Goſpel, proteſting that I will liue and die in that Faith which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me, hauing no other hope nor refuge but onlye to his free adoption, wherein my whole ſaluation is laid, embracing the grace that he hath giuen me in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, accepting the merite of his death and paſſion, to the ende that thereby all my ſinnes may be buried, and beſeching him ſo to waſh and purge me with the bloude of this great redea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which was poured out for all pore ſinners, that I may appeare before his face, as bearing his Image. I proteſt alſo that I haue endeuored me, (according to the meaſure of the grace that he hath giuen me) to teach purely his worde, as well in Sermons as in wryting, and to expound the holy Scriptures faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. And likewiſe in all the diſputations that I haue had with the enimies of the truthe, I neuer vſed cautel nor Sophiſtry, but haue proceded plainly in the maintenaunce of his quarell. But alas, the
<pb facs="tcp:1889:30"/> wil that I haue had, and the zeale, if I moughte ſo call it, hath bene ſo cold and ſlacke, that I finde me greatly endetted in all, and thorow all: and were not his infinite goodneſſe, all the affection that I haue had, were nothing elſe but ſmoke: yea thoſe graces which he hath beſtowed vpon me, woulde yelde me more faulty: ſo that my recourſe is, to that that he being father of mercy, will be, and ſhew him ſelf fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſo pore a ſinner. As concerning the reſt, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that after my deceaſſe, my body may be buried according to the cuſtome, to abide and wait for the day of the bleſſed reſurrection. Concerning the ſmal portion of goods, which God hathe giuen me here to diſpoſe, I doe ordaine and appoynt for my only heir, my welbeloued brother, Antonie Caluin, only for credites ſake, giuing him for all his part, the cuppe that I had of Monſieur de Varranes, praying him therwith to content himſelf (as I am aſſured he wil) ſeing that he knoweth wel that I doe it for no cauſe els, but to the end that that litle which I leaue, may remain to his children. Then, I bequeath to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ten Crowns, and to the purſe of the pore ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers asmuch. Alſo to Iane, daughter to Charles Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan, &amp; of my halfe ſiſter, to wit on the fathers ſide, the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of ten Crownes. Then to Samuel and Iohn, ſonnes to my ſaid brother, euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> .40. <hi>Crownes, &amp; to my Neeces, Anne, Suſan and Dorothee, either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> .30. <hi>Crownes. As touching my Nephew Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid their brother, bicauſe he hath bene alwais light &amp; raſh, I giue him but</hi> .20. <hi>Crownes for his chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb facs="tcp:1889:30"/> It is in effect all the goods that God hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, according to my rate and eſtimation, as well of my Bookes and moueables, with veſſel and all other things. Notwithſtanding, if it amounte to more, I would it wer diſtributed among my Nephewes and Neeces, not excluding at all Dauid, if God giue him grace to become more modeſt and ſtaied But I beleue as touching this article, there ſhalbe no great a do, namely when my dettes ſhall be paid, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I haue charged my brother, vpon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e I truſt, naming him executor of this preſent Teſtament, with reuerend Laurent of Normandy: giuing them full power and authoritye, to make an Inuentorye without forme of lawe, and to ſell my moueables, to make money to fulfill the contentes of this my will, written this</hi> .25. <hi>of April</hi> .1564. <hi>So is it, Iohn Caluin.</hi> After that it was wrytten as before, at the very inſtant, the ſaid renoumed Caluin did ſeale it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his owne ſeale, as ſone as it was wrytten. And on the morowe being the .26. of April, the yere aboue wrytten, the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noumed Caluin did cauſe me to be called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to him, being there togither preſent, theſe famous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Theodore de Beza, Raymond Chauuet, Michel Cop. Lois Enoch, Nicolas Coladon, Iaques de Bordes,</hi> Miniſters of the worde of God in this Church, and that famous man Henry Scringer profeſſor of Artes, al Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geoſes of Geneua, in the preſence of whom
<pb facs="tcp:1889:31"/> he declared that hee had cauſed me to wryte by him and after his pronunciation, the ſayd Teſtamente in the very forme and woordes aboue written: praying me to reade it in his preſence and in the preſence of them that were ther required and deſiced to the ſame effect: which I did all aloud word by word: after the reading whereof, hee declared that ſuch was his wil and laſt diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, willing to haue the ſame obſerued, and (for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter auctorizing hereof) did deſire and requeſt the aboue named to ſubſcribe the ſame with me, which was alſo done the day and yeare aboue written, in Geneua, in the ſtreat cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Chanons ſtreat, and in his dwelling houſe, In witneſſe wherof, and for proofe of the ſame, (as reaſon is) I haue written in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme aforeſayd, this preſent Teſtamente, to make him ready for whom ſo euer the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution thereof ſhall belong vnto, vnder the common ſeale of our very honorable Lords and Superiors, &amp; mine accuſtomed Signe manuell, So is it ſigned. <hi>P. Cheuelat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seing that the ſhortneſſe of his wind did encreaſe more and more, he deſired my Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the foure Sindiques, and the whole lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ordinary Counſell, as they are called, to come and ſee hym togither: and when they
<pb facs="tcp:1889:31"/> were come, hee made to them an excellente declaration of the ſingular graces that they had receiued of God, and of the greate and extreme daungers from the which they had bene preſerued, which he could well declare to them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poynt to poynt, as he that knew the whole better than any man, and did put them in minde of diuers neceſſary thinges concerning God, touching the gouernment of their charge: to be ſhort, hee did the office of a true ſeruant and Prophet of God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting the ſinceritie of the doctrine that hee had taught them, aſſuring them agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tempeſts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were at hand, if they would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue on fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good to better. And then he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them in generall &amp; in particuler, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all his offences, which none euer found ſo grieuous as hee did: he tooke them al by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande, I know not whether there mought haue happened to theſe Lordes a more dolefull ſpectacle or ſight, which they al dyd eſteeme, (&amp; good cauſe why, concerning his charge,) as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, &amp; in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as their owne father, ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had knowen and framed a great peece of theire youth. The Fryday the <hi>.20.</hi> of Aprill, all the brethren Miniſters bothe of the towne and countrey beeing aduertiſed at his requeſte,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:32"/> came togither to his chamber, to whome he gaue a great and long exhortation, wherof the ſubſtance and effect was, that they ſhuld perſeuer in the well doing of theyre duetye after hys Deathe, and that they ſhoulde not faynt, ſeing GOD would both mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn the towne and his Church, albeit they were threatned in many behalfes: and alſo that they ſhould ſuffer no malice or diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to raigne among them, but charitie by all meanes poſſible, and that they ſhould be of perfect accord among themſelues, &amp; that they ſhoulde acknowledge howe greatelye they were bound to that Churche, into the which God had called them, and that there ought nothing to turn them back: for thoſe which haue taſted the truth and wyll leaue it, may finde excuſes vnder the ground, but God wil not be mocked. To this he added a recitall of hys entrie and comming to thys Churche, and of his conuerſation therein: ſaying, that when he came thither, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell was there preached, but thynges were farre out of order, &amp; that the greateſt fruit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Goſpel had brought forth, was the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king downe of the Idolles: but there were there many wicked people, &amp; he was enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to receiue many iniuries: but God did
<pb facs="tcp:1889:32"/> alwayes ſtrengthen him to go thorow w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it, albeit that of his owne nature he was fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: and hee repeated twice or thrice theſe wordes, I aſſure you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of mine own nature I am timorous &amp; fearfull. Alſo he put them in remembrauuce, that when he came from Strauſbourgh hyther, hee entred into thys vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as by conſtraynt, and ſeing no great likelyhoode of anye fruite to come, nor yet knowing what God woulde worke in that behalfe, and in deede that he had paſſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny harde things, but continuing on ſtyll, in tyme hee ſawe the bleſſing of God vpon his labour: he would then that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould waxe ſtrong in hys vocation, and kepe good order, and that they ſhould haue good regard to the people to holde them in continuall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the true doctrine, and that they had alwayes among them Godly men, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit that it coulde not bee auoyded, but that there muſte bee euill perſones and rebelles among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, &amp; that this ſhould ſhew vs very faulty in the ſight of God, if the things being come to ſo good paſſe, ſhoulde after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde fall into decay by our negligence. As touching the reſte, hee proteſted that hee had euer bene of one true affection wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of his brethren, and deſired the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb facs="tcp:1889:33"/> hym if that at any time they had ſene in him any frowardneſſe during his ſickneſſe, and gaue them great thankes, (as often ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes hee vſed,) for that they dyd ſupply hys place in preaching. In the end hee toke them by the hand one after another, whiche was wyth ſo greate ſorrowe and bytterneſſe of heart to euery of them, that I can not call it to minde wythoute greate and extreme ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Maij, hauing receyued let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from M. William Farell, Miniſter at Neufchaſtell, (of whome heeretofore hath bene made mention,) and vnderſtanding that hee was minded to viſit him, being of the age of foure Score yeare and more, hee wrote to hym in this ſorte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be it vvell vvyth you my very good and deare Brother: and ſeing that it pleaſeth GOD that you ſhall remaine after mee, vvell maye you lyue, hauing alvvayes in minde our Vnitie, the fruite vvhereof at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth vpon vs in Heauen, according to the profit therof that the Church of GOD hath enioyed. I vvyll in no vvyſe that you trauayle to ſee mee, for I dravve my breath
<pb facs="tcp:1889:33"/> vvyth great payne, and doe continuallye looke vvhen my breath ſhal fayle me. It is ſufficient that I liue and dye to CHRIST, vvhich is a gayne to his both in life and death, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend you agayne to God vvyth all the Brethren in thoſe partes. From Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua this ſecond of Maij .1564. By vvholly yours Iohn Caluin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From that time forth his ſickneſſe euen to hys death was nothing elſe but a continual Prayer, notwythſtanding that hee was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in paynes, hauing often tymes in his mouth theſe woordes of the Pſalme <hi>.39. <hi>Tacui Domine quia feciſti.</hi>
               </hi> I held my peace O Lorde, bycauſe it is thou that haſt done it. Other times he would ſay of the <hi>.38.</hi> Chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Eſay. <hi>Gemebam ſicut Columba,</hi> I dyd lamente as doth the Doue. Another tyme ſpeaking to me, he ſayd and cryed out, Lord thou punniſheſt me, but it is ſufficient for me that it is thy hand. Many were deſirous to come and ſee hym, but it had bene neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to haue kept the gate open day &amp; night, to haue fulfylled their deſyre. But hee fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeing that, and knowing that the ſhortneſſe of winde woulde not ſuffer hym to doe that which willingly he would: beſide that alſo,
<pb facs="tcp:1889:34"/> not well liking the curioſity of many, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought them to contente them ſelues and to pray to God for him, and to ſuffer him ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to reſte: yea, when I came to ſee hym, albeit that I was very welcome to hym, yet notwythſtanding, conſidering my charge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had, hee gaue me to vnderſtand fully, that he would not in any wyſe that hys particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler cauſe ſhould occupy me in any reſpect: in ſuch ſort that taking leaue of me, hee would often ſay that he made conſcience to let mee, were it neuer ſo little, albeit that hee was glad to ſee me: but his nature was alwaies ſuch, that he feared to ſtay (were it neuer ſo lyttle) the profit of the church, and to trouble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt that mought be his frends, although ther were nothing in the world more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them than to employ themſelues to doe him pleaſure.</p>
            <p>He continued in this ſort, comforting him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe and his friendes, vntill the Fryday the xix. of Maij, next before the Supper of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſte, on the which day bycauſe it was the cuſtome of this Church, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the Miniſters ſhould aſſemble them to yelde as it were an accompt of their life and doctrine, and then in token of friendſhip they take their repaſt togyther, hee was contented that the ſupper
<pb facs="tcp:1889:34"/> ſhould be made at his houſe, where hee cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf to brought in a chaire, as he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in among them he ſpake theſe wordes, My brethren I come now to ſee you for my farewel: for after this time I wil neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e more to table. This was to vs a piteous entrie, albeit that he himſelf ſayd the prayer as well as he could, &amp; enforced him to make vs merry, not being able to eate but very little: yet before ſupper was ended, he toke his leaue, and cauſed himſelf to be caried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into his chamber, which was at hand ſpeaking theſe wordes wyth as pleaſaunt a countenaunce as he could, A wall betwene both ſhall not let at all, but that I wyll bee ioyned wyth you in ſpirit. It came to paſſe euen as hee had ſayde: for vntyll that very day, what dyſeaſe ſo euer he had, hee would be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of his bed and brought in a chair to his little table, but after this night he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhifted from lying vppon his backe, ſo greatly weakned, notwythſtanding that he was leane of himſelf, that there remayned in manner nothing but onely lyfe, ſauing that he was very little chaunged of face: but chiefly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhortnes of hys winde did ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him, that it cauſed his continual prayers and conſolations rather to ſeeme ſighes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1889:35"/> words to be vnderſtode: and he was of ſuch a countenance, that hys only loke did plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtify wyth what fayth and hope he was furniſhed. The daye that hee died it ſeemed that hee ſpake better and more at hys eaſe, but it was the laſte enforcement of nature: for that night about eight of the clock, euen ſodaynely, appeared the tokens of preſente Death, whereof I had ſpeedily worde, (for I was but newly departed from him,) &amp; run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thither wyth certayn of my brethren, as ſone as I came, I found that he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready yelded vp his ſpirit, ſo quietly that hee dyd neuer rattle, but ſpake playnely euen to hys very death, wyth perfect vnderſtanding and iudgement, without euer ſtirring hand or foote: hee ſeemed rather to be a ſleepe than dead. Beholde as in an inſtante howe that very day the ſunne dyd ſet, and the greateſt lighte that was in the worlde for the buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Church of GOD, was taken into Heauen. And we may well ſay that in our tyme by one onely man it hath pleaſed God to reach vs both to lyue &amp; to dye well. The Night following, and the Daye alſo, ther was great lamentation thorowout the towne: For the whole bodye thereof did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle the Prophet of the Lorde: the poore
<pb facs="tcp:1889:35"/> flock of the Church did weepe for the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their faythfull Paſtor: The Schole lamented her true Maiſter and teacher: and all in generall did bewaile their very father and comforter next vnto GOD. Many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired that they might ſee yet once his face, as men that could not leaue hym neyther dead nor liuing. There were alſo diuers ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers newely come from farre of to ſee hym, which when they coulde not, for that men thought that he wold not ſo ſoone haue died, deſired greatly to ſee him deade as hee was, and made great inſtance: but to auoyde all euyll reportes and ſpeach, he was buried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eyght of the clocke in the morning, and at two of the clocke at afternone according as he had appoynted, hee was carried accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde called the great or large Pallaice, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pompe or any adoe at al, where he now lyeth abiding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrection, which hee hath taught vs, and hath ſo conſtantly hoped for. The body was accompanied by the greateſt part of thoſe that were in the towne, of men of all eſtates, which dyd the more lamente hym, bycauſe there was ſmall likelyhode to recouer (at the leaſt of a long tyme,) ſuche a great loſſe. He liued as touching this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb facs="tcp:1889:36"/> lyfe, the ſpace of ſyxe and fyftye yeares, lacking one Moneth and thyrtene Dayes. Whereof he ſpent the iuſte one halfe in the holye Miniſterie, preaching and writing, without euer chaunging anye thing, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing or adding to or from the doctrine that he taught the firſt day of his Miniſtery, with ſuch power of the Spirite of God, that neuer wicked man was able to heare him without trembling, nor good man without louing and honoring him.</p>
            <p>There reſteth nowe no more but euen as it hath pleaſed God to make him to ſpeake continually by his ſo learned and holy writings, that he may ſo be heard of the poſteritie to the ende of the world, at what time wee ſhal ſee our God euen as he is, to liue and to raigne eternally w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. So be it.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Geneua <date>this .19. of Auguſt .1564.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:36"/>
            <head>¶ Aduertiſement.</head>
            <p>FOR bycauſe that there is none of the Faythfull, who woulde not gladlye vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the truthe of the number of Bookes that haue bene written by the late M. Iohn Caluin, to the end that hereafter men be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, as is wel knowen that the like hath hapned to the writinges of great and excellent perſonages that men haue falſely ſet foorth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnder their name: It hath ſeemed therefore good to ioyne to thys a Catalogue, as well of hys bookes and writings in Latine &amp; French already Imprinted, as of thoſe that yet are not, at the leaſt of as many as may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to minde.</p>
            <p>Thoſe which are not yet in French are marked wyth thys marke.*.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="catalogue_of_Calvins_works">
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:37"/>
            <head>The Catalogue of the Bookes and wrytings of Maiſter Iohn Caluin.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Commentaries and leſſons in Latin and French al readie imprinted vpon the olde Teſtament.</item>
               <item>Vpon Geneſis.</item>
               <item>Vpon the other foure Bookes of Moyſes in forme of Harmonie.</item>
               <item>Vpon the Booke of Ioſue.</item>
               <item>Vpon all the Pſalmes.</item>
               <item>Vpon Eſaye.</item>
               <item>* Vpon Ieremie.</item>
               <item>Vpon Daniel.</item>
               <item>Vpon the .xij. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are called little Prophetes.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Vpon the new Teſtament, alſo imprinted.</head>
               <item>Vpon the three Euangeliſtes in forme of Harmonie.</item>
               <item>Vpon Saint Iohn.</item>
               <item>Vpon the Actes of the Apoſtles.</item>
               <item>Vpon all the Epiſtles of Saint Paule.</item>
               <item>Vpon the Epiſtle to the Hebrues.</item>
               <item>Vpon the Epiſtles Canonicall of S. Peter, Saint Iohn, Saint Iames and S. Iude.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:1889:37"/>
               <head>The Catalogue of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons imprinted, which men gathered when he preached.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Vpon Iob.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the Commaundements.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the Octonaries of the 119. Pſalme.</item>
                  <item>Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſong of Ezechias in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .38. ca. of Eſay.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Harmonie of the three Euangeliſtes.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the .10. and .11. Chapiters of the fyrſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the Epiſtle to the Galathians.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the Epiſtle to the Epheſians.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the Epiſtles to Timothe &amp; to Tite.</item>
                  <item>Alſo many Sermons of the Byrth, Paſſion, Death, Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Aſcenſion of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>Foure Sermons entreating of matters ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable for our time.</item>
                  <item>A Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made in the Church of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua, of the prouidence and eternall elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Sermons vpon the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not imprinted.</head>
                  <item>Vpon Geneſis.</item>
                  <item>Vpon Deuteronomie.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the two bookes of Samuel.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1889:38"/>
                  <item>Vpon the firſt booke of the Kings.</item>
                  <item>Vpon many Pſalmes.</item>
                  <item>Certaine ſummes of Congregations made vpon Ioſue, gathered euen as hee did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate of and handle the textes.</item>
                  <item>Vpon Eſaie.</item>
                  <item>Vpon Ieremie.</item>
                  <item>Vpon Ezechiel.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the later eyght Chapiters of Daniel.</item>
                  <item>Vpon ſeuen of the twelue little Prophetes.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Vpon the Newe Teſtament.</head>
                  <item>Certaine Sermons moe vpon the Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the three Euangeliſtes.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the Actes.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the two Epiſtles to the Corinthians.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the Epiſtle to the Theſſalonians.</item>
                  <item>Vpon certaine Chapiters of the ende of the Epiſtle to the Hebrues.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Leſſons in Frenche not yet Imprinted.</head>
                  <item>Vpon the Pſalmes, from the .37. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende.</item>
                  <item>Vpon Ieremie.</item>
                  <item>Vpon the .20. firſt Chapiters of Ezechiel as well in Latin as in Frenche.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:1889:38"/>
               <head>A Catalogue of other Bookes &amp; treatiſes which he hath made in ſundry times and ſundry places.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>* A Commentarie vpon the Booke of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca, touching the vertue of Clemencie.</item>
                  <item>His Chriſtian Inſtitution.</item>
                  <item>A treatiſe againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> errour of ſuch as thinke that the ſoules doe ſleepe after they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</item>
                  <item>Two Epiſtles, the one to flee Idolatrie, the other of the duety of a Chriſtian man.</item>
                  <item>An aunſwere to the letter which the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Sadolet wrote to the Lordes and people of Geneua.</item>
                  <item>A treatiſe of the ſupper of the Lorde.</item>
                  <item>* Certaine verſes in Latin of the victorie of Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>A Cathechiſme for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtruction of Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
                  <item>A manner of Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with the common prayers, and the maner how to celebrate the Mariage.</item>
                  <item>A defence of the pure doctrine concerning free will, againſt the calumnies of Albert Pighius.</item>
                  <item>Annotations vpon the fatherly aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made by the Pope Paule the thirde to the Emperour Charles the fift.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1889:39"/>
                  <item>Antidote or preſeruatiue againſt the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the facultie of the Sorboniſtes of Parris.</item>
                  <item>A treatiſe or ſupplication to the Emperor concerning the neceſſitie of the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church.</item>
                  <item>Againſt the Anabaptiſtes and Libertines, with an Epiſtle to the faithfull of Roan, againſt a Frier a Libertine.</item>
                  <item>An Aduertiſement concerning the bodies &amp; Reliques of Saints &amp; what profit there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of them if they be diligently kept.</item>
                  <item>A treatiſe in flie ſuperſtitions, with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of the falſe Nicodemites, with the aunſwere of the Miniſters of Zuriche.</item>
                  <item>Antidote to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Actes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſell of Trent.</item>
                  <item>The very true meane to pacifie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> troubles &amp; to reforme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Interim.</item>
                  <item>An Aduertiſement againſt the Aſtrologie Iudiciall, and ſuch curioſities, which at this daye heare the ſwaye in manner tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowoute the worlde.</item>
                  <item>An agreement concerning the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</item>
                  <item>A treatiſe of Offences.</item>
                  <item>Of the eternall Prouidence of God.</item>
                  <item>Againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deteſtable errors of Michel Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet a Spaniarde.</item>
                  <item>*Three aduertiſements to Weſtphalus.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1889:39"/>
                  <item>* Againſt Hethuſius and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> error of Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carus.</item>
                  <item>* Againſt Valentin Gentil.</item>
                  <item>* Aunſwere to the calumnies which Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Caſtalion did ſowe abrode.</item>
                  <item>*An other ſhort aunſwere to other calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the ſame man.</item>
                  <item>A Congratulation to the reuerende prieſt, Maiſter Gabriel de Sacoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Lions chiefe Miniſter.</item>
                  <item>*An aunſwere to a certaine fine and ſubtil Neutre.</item>
                  <item>*An aunſwere to the outrages of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cis Baldwin an Apoſtate.</item>
                  <item>*A ſhort Aduertiſement to the Faithfull of Polonia.</item>
                  <item>*An Epiſtle to the foreſaide, for the Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſayde Aduertiſement.</item>
                  <item>An aunſwere to a certaine Hollander, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the people of the low countrey.</item>
                  <item>A Reformation to put to ſilence a certaine raſcall named Antonie Catalan.</item>
                  <item>A Confeſſion of the faith in the name of all the reformed Churches of the Realme of Fraunce, made during the Warres, to deliuer to the Emperor.</item>
                  <item>Alſo a great number of Letters, counſels, aduertiſements and aunſweres, as well
<pb facs="tcp:1889:40"/> in Latin as in Frenche, to diuers perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſundry qualitie and eſtate: wherein is entreated of diuers matters, which (one day if it pleaſe God y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it maye be ſet forth into light) men may then better ſee what was the wiſedome, promptneſſe, ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler iudgement, and the maruellous and diuine graces, that were in this Faithful Seruant of God.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the firſt Sheete.</head>
            <p>A .iij. leaf, ij. ſide, iij. line, for more reade me.</p>
            <p>A .iiij. leaf, firſt ſide, x. line. for that reade the.</p>
            <p>A .v. leafe, ij. fide, xvij. line, for anye reade euery.</p>
            <p>A .vij. leafe, ij. ſide, vj. line, for Guiſe reade Swiſſe, &amp; for Guiſians read Griſons.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1889:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Whitecroſſe ſtreate by Henry Denham, for Lucas Harriſon, dwelling in Paules Chuchyarde, at the Signe of the Crane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini. <hi>1564,</hi> Nouembris <hi>.4.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
